Guide to The Southern Review Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The Southern Review records
1935-1943
YCAL MSS 694
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(7 boxes)
The Southern Review records contain correspondence and other papers documenting activity at the influential literary journal from 1935 to 1943. Correspondence consists chiefly of original letters from authors and carbons of outgoing letters from the editors. Most incoming letters are addressed to the founding editors, Cleanth Brooks and Robert Penn Warren, but there are letters to others as well, including Albert Erskine, Robert Lowell, and Charles W. Pipkin. There is also some correspondence with literary agents, publishers, and others relating to or on behalf of authors and writings, including corrected drafts and proofs. Other materials include financial and legal records, unidentified writings, and a catalog of publications, including lists of unread and returned manuscripts.
Southern Review (Organization)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cleanth Brooks and Robert Penn Warren, 1952.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection available on microfilm.
Associated Materials
Cleanth Brook Papers (YCAL MSS 30). Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Robert Penn Warren Papers (YCAL MSS 51). Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The Southern Review
The Southern Review is a literary journal published by Louisiana State University since 1935. The journal was co-founded by Robert Penn Warren and Cleanth Brooks and co-edited by Warren and Brooks until 1942.
Scope and Contents
The Southern Review records contain correspondence and other papers documenting activity at the influential literary journal from 1935 to 1943. Correspondence consists chiefly of original letters from authors and carbons of outgoing letters from the editors. Most incoming letters are addressed to the founding editors, Cleanth Brooks and Robert Penn Warren, but there are letters to others as well, including Albert Erskine, Robert Lowell, and Charles W. Pipkin. There is also some correspondence with literary agents, publishers, and others relating to or on behalf of authors and writings, including corrected drafts and proofs. Other materials include financial and legal records, unidentified writings, and a catalogue of publications, including lists of unread and returned manuscripts.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1935-1942. II. Other Papers, 1935-1943.
Southern review (Baton Rouge, La.); American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century -- Periodicals -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Authors and publishers -- United States; Little magazines -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Brooks, Cleanth, 1906-1994; Erskine, Albert, 1911-1993; Lowell, Robert, 1917-1977; Pipkin, Charles W. (Charles Wooten), 1899-1941; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-1989; Louisiana State University (Baton Rouge, La.)
- Correspondence, 1935-1942; Series I; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists chiefly of original letters from authors and carbons of outgoing letters from the editors. Most incoming letters are addressed to the founding editors, Cleanth Brooks and Robert Penn Warren, but there are letters to others as well, including Albert Erskine, Robert Lowell, and Charles W. Pipkin. There is also some correspondence with literary agents, publishers, and others relating to or on behalf of authors and writings, including corrected drafts and proofs.
  Additional letter general files can be found at the end of the alphabetized run of files.
  - "A" general, 1935-1942 (Box 1)
  - Abbe, George, 1934-1941 (Box 1)
  - Adams, W. G. S., 1937 May 7 (Box 1)
  - Adler, Mortimer J., 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Agar, Herbert, 1935-1940 (Box 1)
  - Agee, James, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - Algren, Nelson, 1940-1942; 3 (Box 1)
  - Auden, W. H., 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Ayres, C. E., 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - "B" general, 1935-1942, undated (Box 1)
  - Baker, Howard, 1935-1941 (Box 1)
  - Barber, C. L., 1939 (Box 1)
  - Barrett, William, 1939-1942, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Barzun, Jacques, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Beals, Carleton, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Beard, Charles A., 1937-1940, undated (Box 1)
  - Beatty, Richmond, 1935, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Belgion, Montgomery, 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Belitt, Ben, 1940-1941; 2 (Box 1)
  - Bentley, Eric Russell, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Berryman, John, 1937-1941 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, John Peale, 1935-1941 (Box 1)
  - Blackmur, R. P., 1935-1942 (Box 1)
  - Boone, Jack, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  - Botkin, B. A., 1935-1938 (Box 1)
  - Boyle, Kay, 1935, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm, 1940, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Brinton, Crane, 1935-1941 (Box 1)
  - Bronson, Bertrand, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Buchanan, Scott, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Burke, Kenneth, 1935-1941 (Box 1)
  - "C-F" general, 1936-1942, undated (Box 2)
  - Cahn, Harriet, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Caldwell, Erskine, 1935, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Chiappe, Andrew, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Chilton, Eleanor, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - Clark, John Abbot, 1936-1941 (Box 2)
  - Codman, Florence, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Conley, John, 1935-1938 (Box 2)
  - Corry, Andrew, 1935-1940 (Box 2)
  - Couch, W. T., 1935-1942 (Box 2)
  - Coulborn, Rushton, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - Craven, Avery, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Cummings, E. E., 1935 (Box 2)
  - Dabbs, James McBride, 1935-1938 (Box 2)
  - Dabney, Virginius, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Daiches, David, 1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Dannenbaum, Raymond, 1935-1941 (Box 2)
  - Davidson, Donald, 1934-1941 (Box 2)
  - Davis, H. L., 1936 (Box 2)
  - DeJong, David, 1937-1941 (Box 2)
  - Devlin, Denis, 1941-1942, undated (Box 2)
  - Dewey, John, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Dobree, Bonamy, 1935-1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Dodd, W. E., 1938, undated (Box 2)
  - Donahoe, Edward, 1935-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Douglas, C. H., 1935 August (Box 2)
  - Dupee, F. W., 1938-1940 (Box 2)
  - Eastman, Max, 1937-1940; 2 (Box 2)
  - Eberhart, Richard G., 1938-1942; 4 (Box 2)
  - Eliot, T. S., 1935-1941 (Box 2)
  - Elliott, William Yandell, 1935-1939 (Box 2)
  - Empson, William, 1937-1940 (Box 2)
  - "F" general, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Farnham, Willard, 1936, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Farrell, James T., 1937-1941 (Box 2)
  - Faulkner, William, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Feibleman, James K., 1937-1941 (Box 2)
  - Fergusson, Francis, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Ferril, Thomas, 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - Field, S. S., 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - Fite, Mary Elizabeth, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Fitts, Dudley, 1935, undated (Box 2)
  - Fitzell, Lincoln, 1935-1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Fitzgerald, F. Scott, 1935, undated (Box 2)
  - Fitzgerald, William, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Fletcher, John Gould, 1935-1938 (Box 3)
  - Flexner, Abraham, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Flint, F. Cudworth, 1935-1942 (Box 3)
  - Flynn, John T., 1936-1938 (Box 3)
  - Ford, Charles Henri, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Ford, Ford Maddox, 1935-1939 (Box 3)
  - [Forgotson?], Shirley, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Foster, Charles Howell, 1941 November 11 (Box 3)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1941; 2 (Box 3)
  - Frank, Joseph, 1941, undated (Box 3)
  - Frankenberg, Lloyd, 1941-1942; 2 (Box 3)
  - Friedrich, C. J., 1939 (Box 3)
  - Frierson, William C., 1937 (Box 3)
  - Fuchs, Daniel, 1941-1942; 2 (Box 3)
  - "G-H" general, 1935-1942 (Box 3)
  - Gair, Sidney, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Gibbs, Barbara, 1935-1938 (Box 3)
  - Gilman, William, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Godchaux, Elma, 1935-1940 (Box 3)
  - Gooch, Robert Kent, 1935, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Gordon, Caroline, 1935-1939 (Box 3)
  - Gordon, Don, 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Gregory, Horace, 1935-1941 (Box 3)
  - Hacker, Louis, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Haines, George, 1941-1942; 2 (Box 3)
  - Hart, Liddell, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Hatfield, Henry, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Healy, J. V., 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Heilman, Robert Bechtold, undated (Box 3)
  - Herring, Harriet L., 1940 (Box 3)
  - Hinton, James, 1941-1942; 2 (Box 3)
  - Hollis, Christopher, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
  - Hook, Sidney, 1937-1940; 2 (Box 3)
  - Hopkins, Joseph, 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Horrell, Joe, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
  - Horton, Philip, 1936-1938 (Box 3)
  - Ingalls, Jeremy, 1941 January 18 (Box 3)
  - "J-L" general, 1935-1942 (Box 3)
  - Jarrell, Randall, 1935-1940 (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Dean, 1936-1938 (Box 3)
  - Josephson, Matthew, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
  - Kees, Weldon, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Kelly, John J., 1939 (Box 4)
  - Kendrick, Benjamin, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1935, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Knights, L. C., 1938-1941 (Box 4)
  - Krey, Laura, 1935-1939 (Box 4)
  - Lanier, Lyle, 1937-1939 (Box 4)
  - Laski, Harold, 1935 July 29 (Box 4)
  - Lattimore, Richmond, 1935-1939; 2 (Box 4)
  - Leavis, F. R., 1935-1940 (Box 4)
  - Lerner, Max, 1937-1941 (Box 4)
  - Levin, Harry, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Lindley, Ernest, 1937, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Lutz, Ralph, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Lynes, Carlos, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Lytle, Andrew, 1935-1941, undated (Box 4)
  - "M-P" general, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - McCarthy, Mary, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - MacDonald, Dwight, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - McGinnis, Allen, 1935-1939 (Box 4)
  - MacIntyre, Carlyle, 1936-1942; 2 (Box 4)
  - MacIver, Robert, 1935-1939 (Box 4)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1935 (Box 4)
  - MacNeice, Louis, 1939 May 4 (Box 4)
  - Madison, Charles, 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Mallan, Lloyd, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1937, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Mathews, Jackson, 1939-1941 (Box 4)
  - Matthiessen, F. O., 1936-1941 (Box 4)
  - Mendenhall, Marjorie, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Meredith, William, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Merriman, Roger, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Merton, Thomas, undated (Box 4)
  - Milburn, George, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
  - Miles, Josephine, 1937-1941 (Box 4)
  - Miller, Caroline, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Millis, Walter, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Millspaugh, C. A., 1939-1941 (Box 4)
  - Mitchell, Braodus, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Mizener, Arthur, 1938-1941 (Box 4)
  - Monk, Samuel, 1936-1941 (Box 4)
  - Moore, Harry Thornton, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1935, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Morley, Felix, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Mortimer, J. de C., 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - Moses, William, 1935-1939 (Box 4)
  - Muller, Herbert J., 1938-1941 (Box 4)
  - Munson, Gorham, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Nevins, Allan, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Nicholson, Norman, 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - Nixon, H. C., 1935 (Box 4)
  - O'Donnell, George Marion, 1935-1940; 2 (Box 4)
  - Ogburn, W. F., 1937 (Box 4)
  - O'Hara, John, 1925 March 23 (Box 4)
  - Owsley, Frank, 1935-1940 (Box 4)
  - Parkes, Henry B., 1936-1941, undated (Box 5)
  - Parks, Edd, 1937-1940 (Box 5)
  - Pasinetti, Pierre, 1937-1940 (Box 5)
  - Person, W. T., 1937-1938 (Box 5)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1935-1942 (Box 5)
  - Praz, Mario, 1936-1937 (Box 5)
  - Prokosch, Frederic, 1938-1939 (Box 5)
  - Putnam, Howard Phelps, 1935-1938 (Box 5)
  - Quigley, Harold, 1936 (Box 5)
  - "R-S" general, 1935-1942 (Box 5)
  - Radford, Manson, 1936-1938, undated (Box 5)
  - Rahv, Philip, 1937-1942; 2 (Box 5)
  - Ramsdell, Charles W., 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Ransom, John Crowe, 1935-1942, undated (Box 5)
  - Read, Herbert, 1935-1936 (Box 5)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1941, undated (Box 5)
  - Richards, I. A., 1935-1941 (Box 5)
  - Riegel, O. W., 1935-1936 (Box 5)
  - Roberts, Michael, 1938-1939 (Box 5)
  - Roellinger, Francis X., 1941-1942; 2 (Box 5)
  - Roelofs, Howard Dykema, 1939-1941 (Box 5)
  - Rogers, Lindsay, 1936-1940 (Box 5)
  - Rosenfeld, Paul, 1938-1939; 2 (Box 5)
  - Rukeyser, Muriel, 1939-1941 (Box 5)
  - Swan, Emma, 1940; 2 (Box 5)
  - "T-V" general, 1937, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Tate, Allen, 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Tumin, Arthur, 1941-1942; 2 (Box 5)
  - Unger, Leonard, 1941; 3 (Box 5)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1941; 4 (Box 5)
  - Watkins, Ann, 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Wellek, Rene, 1941-1942; 2 (Box 5)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Wolfe, Thomas, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Yeats, W. B., 1935-1937, undated (Box 5)
  - Young, Marguerite, 1940-1941; 2 (Box 5)
  - "W-Z" general, 1940-1942 (Box 5)
  - "A-W" general, [circa 1935-1942]; 20 (Box 6)
  - "Agents letters to SR submitting MSS", 1940-1942 (Box 6)
- Other Papers, 1935-1943; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by folder heading.
  Series II. Other Papers contains financial and legal records, unidentified writings, a catalogue of publications, including lists of unread and returned manuscripts, and other papers.
  - Budget data, 1940-1941, undated (Box 7)
  - Business (general), 1941-1942, undated (Box 7)
  - Catalogue of MSS, [circa 1940-1942] (Box 7)
  - Copyright materials, 1935-1942, undated (Box 7)
  - Data re. advertising, 1940-1942, undated (Box 7)
  - Data re. bank departs, 1940-1942, undated (Box 7)
  - Material relating to the demise of the Southern Review, 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous & unidentified mss, undated (Box 7)
  - Mss returned, [1936-1942?] (Box 7)
  - Petitions & letters regarding demise, 1942 (Box 7)
  - Press reviews (copied), undated (Box 7)
  - Re. merger with Kenyon Review, 1942-1943, undated (Box 7)